1925年
英王乔治五世统治着世界四分之一的人口
他命自己的次子约克公爵
为在伦敦温布利举行的帝国博览会致闭幕词
国王的演讲
殿下  离您出场还有两分钟
You are live in two minutes, Your Royal Highness.
殿下
Sir?
在话筒前讲话就可以了  阁下
At the microphone, Do your work Sir.
我相信您会做得很出色  只要别急
I am sure you will be splendid. Just take your time.
去吧
Time to go.
下午好
Good afternoon.
现在是由BBC国家电台及大英帝国电台
This is the BBC National Programme and Empire Services
为您直播在温布利体育场举行的
taking you to Wembley Stadium
帝国博览会闭幕式
for the Closing Ceremony of the Empire Exhibition.
约克公爵殿下将在此宣读
where His Royal Highness the
来自他父王
Duke of York will read a message from his Father;
乔治五世的祝词
His Majesty, King George V.
五十八个英属殖民地和领地的参加
58 British Colonies and Dominions have taken part,
使之成为全世界最盛大的博览会
making this the largest Exhibition staged anywhere in the world.
记住  殿下  指示灯会闪三下
Remember Sir, Three flashes;
然后亮红灯  说明广播开始
then steady 'red' means you are Live.
收音机问世
Using the new invention of radio,
使国王陛下首次通过无线电
The Opening Ceremony was the first time
在开幕式上发表了演说
his Majesty the King addressed his subjects on the wireless.
第一期结束时
At the close of the first Season,
王储威尔士亲王殿下
The heir to the throne His Royal
也发表了首次广播演说
Highness the Prince of Wales, made his first broadcast.
今天  他的弟弟
And today, his younger brother His Royal Highness,
约克公爵殿下也将首次通过广播
the Duke of York will give his
向大英帝国以及全世界致闭幕词
inaugural broadcast to the Nation and the World.
我收到了
I have received...
国王  国
from his Majesty....t' ek
国王陛下的
...The King.
1934年  伦敦  皮卡迪利大街145号
深深吸进肺里  殿下
Inhale deep into your lungs..Your Royal Highness.
这能放松您的喉咙  是吧
Relaxes your larynx, does it not?
吸烟让您精神放松并给您自信
Cigarette smoking calms the nerves and gives you confidence.
殿下  请您张开手
If Your Highness will be very kind as to open your hand...
这是消过毒的
It's Sterilized. Now..
一  二  三  四  五  六  七
One,two,three,four,five,six,seven.
恕我冒昧
Now...if I may take the liberty?
请把它们含在嘴里
...insert them into your mouth.
抱歉  医生  请问这样做是为了什么
Excuse me, Doctor. What is the purpose of this?
这是传统疗法  它治好了德摩斯梯尼(古希腊雄辩家)
It is the classic approach, it cured Demosthenes.
那是在古希腊
That was in ancient Greece...uh
现在还管用吗
Has it worked since?
现在  请您读一下
Now, if you would be so kind as to read...
这几段话
A wealth of words.
克服那些弹珠的阻碍  殿下
Fight against those marbles, Your Royal Highness.
读出来
Enunciate!
再专心一点  殿下
A little more concentration your Royal Higness.
我差点吞了这些该死的玩意儿
I nearly swallowed the bloody things!
谢谢您  医生
Thank you so much, Doctor,
这非常  有意思
it's been most...hmm interesting.
殿下
Your highness.
含弹珠
Insert marbles!
他怎么不自己含
He can insert his own bloody marbles....!
你不能总这样  博迪
You know, you can't keep doing this, Bertie.
我知道
I know.
答应我  答应我  治疗到此为止
Promise me. Promise me, no more.
哈里街
查普曼医生
L・罗格  语言障碍
你好  有人在吗
Hello. Is anyone there?
我在厕所里
I'm just in the loo.
约翰逊夫人  您来了
Ah, Mrs.Johnson There you are.
抱歉  我这没前台  我喜欢简单
I'm sorry, there's no receptionist. I like to keep things simple.
乐而安贫就是富
Poor and content is rich and rich enough.
-什么  -莎士比亚说的  您好
- Sorry?  - Shakespeare. How are you?
您好
How do you do?
我近来咳嗽不断
Coughing a lot.
这有点棘手  但是  恐怕您迟到了
Now, this is slightly awkward, But.. I'm afraid you're late.
是的  恐怕是的
Yes, I'm afraid I am.
约翰逊先生呢
Where's Mr Johnson?
他不知道我来
He doesn't know I'm here.
这个开头可不好
That's not a promising start.
我丈夫求医无数  皆无好转
Look, my husband has seen everyone to no avail.
恐怕他已经放弃了
Awefully 'fraid he's given up hope.
他还没见过我
He hasn't seen me.
你很自信
You're awfully sure of yourself.
我对每个期望治好的人都满怀信心
Well, I'm sure of anyone who wants to be cured.
当然他想要治好
Of course, he wishes to be cured.
我丈夫  需要在公开场合讲话
My husband is umm.. he's required to speak publicly.
或许他该换个工作
Perhaps he should change jobs?
不行
He can't.
卖身契
Indentured servitude?
差不多
Something of that nature. Yes.
那么  你老公得过来
Well we need to have your hubby pop by...
周二可以
Uh..Tuesday would be good...
他可以跟我说下个人情况
He can give me his personal details
我来做个准确评估  然后开始治疗
and I'll make a frank appraisal and then, We can take it from there.
抱歉  医生
Doctor, forgive me.
我不称他为老公  我们也不过来
I do not have a hubby. We don't pop.
更不对外人讲我们的私生活
And nor do we ever talk about our private lives.
您  必须来我家
You... must come to us.
抱歉  约翰逊夫人  我的地盘听我的
I'm Sorry, Mrs Johnson, my game, my turf, my rules.
你得说服你丈夫
You'll have to talk over this with your husband
然后给我打电话
and then you can speak to me on the telephone.
感谢你来访  再见
Thank you very much for dropping by... Good afternoon.
如果我丈夫是约克公爵呢
And what if my husband were the Duke of York?
约克公爵
The Duke of York?
是的  约克公爵
Yes... the Duke of York.
我以为预约的是约翰逊  抱歉  殿...
I thought the appointment was for Johnson? Forgive me, your ...?
殿下
..Royal Highness.
大战时他用这个姓
Johnson was used during the Great War;
皇家海军不想让敌人知道他在船上
when the Navy didn't want the enemy to know he was aboard.
我被当成敌人吗
Am I...considered the enemy?
是的  如果您不合作  而且你得严格保密
You will be, if you remain unobliging. And you have to have abosolute descretion.
当然  殿下  您是怎么找到我的
Of course. How did you find me, Your Royal Highness?
通过语言矫治协会的会长
The President of society of the Speech Therapists.
艾琳・麦克卢尔  她是我的朋友
Eileen McCleod? She's a sport.
麦克卢尔医生提醒我说
Dr McCleod warned me your
您的澳洲式疗法是异端而且颇有争议
antipodean methods were unorthodox and controversial.
我告诉她  我不爱听那些词
I warned her... those were not my favorite words.
我可以为您丈夫治疗
I can cure your husband.
但用我的办法需要信任和彻底的平等
But for my method to work I need trust and total equality;
并在我的诊室里进行
Here, in the safety of my consultation room.
概不例外
No exceptions.
那么  既然这样
Well then, in that case...
您什么时候可以开始
When can you start?
听起来还是有点刺耳  小伙子
Still sounds a bit rough, mate.
是你让我开得太慢了  老爸
You make me drive too slowly, Dad!
你去桥那边接你妈了吗
Did you pick mum up from bridge?
是的  一整天我都开着车到处跑
Yes, I've hardly been out of the car all day.
今天下午  来了位特别的客人
I had a special visitor this afternoon.
-我可以离桌了吧  -怎么个特别法
- May I please leave this table.  - How special, special?
不行  小蠢蛋
No, You must stay, bored stupid,
你得留下来听你爸妈无聊的谈话
listening to your parents'inane conversation.
-谢谢爸爸  -还有你妈
- Thanks Dad..  - and Mum.
谢谢妈妈
And mom.
-我也走了  -去见简吗
- Me too.  - You meeting Jean?
不是  别人
No, someone else.
博士  博士  你能帮兄弟们洗碗吗
Doctor? Doctor? Can't you help your brother with the washing...
我正忙着呢
I'm fine.
是谁  莱昂内尔
Who's it Lionel?
不能说提它干嘛
Why bring it up if you can't talk about it?
莫特尔  只是一个女人  想帮她丈夫
Myrtle, It's just a woman, looking to help her husband.
还有  我接到一个电话
Oh! And I had a call.
得到一个试镜机会
For an audition.
-我的最爱之一  -所有角色不都是你最爱吗
- One of my favorites.  - Aren't they all?
很有意思的角色
It could be a lot of fun.
我相信你会做得很好
I'm sure you'll be splendid.
是个有威望的剧团
They're a highly regarded group.
来自普特尼
From Putney.
明天读第四章
Tomorrow, Chapter IV.
飞行
The flight
-我都不知道他会飞  -我都等不及了
- Mama, I don't know he can fly at all. - I can't wait
他们能飞走
Oh, they can fly away
不是很幸运吗
Weren't they lucky!
那爸爸讲个故事吧
Now Papa tell a story!
我装企鹅还不行吗
Could I be a penguin instead?
我想听企鹅的故事
Well, now I want a penguin story.
讲个短的
Very quickly.
从前  有两个公主
Once, there were two princesses...
伊丽莎白公主和玛格丽特公主
Princess Elizabeth and Princess Margaret.
她们的爸爸是只企鹅
whose Papa was a penguin.
因为邪恶的女巫对他施了魔咒
This was because he had been turned into one by the wicket witch.
这让他为难
This was an... inconvenient for him..
因为他喜欢用手怀抱两个公主
because he loved to hold his princesses in his arms...
但企鹅不行  因为他长着青鱼般的翅膀
and penguin can't because he has wings like herrings
青鱼没有翅膀
Herrings don't have wings.
企鹅翅膀的形状像青鱼
Penguins have wings which is shaped like herrings
但更糟的是
and make matters worse...
女巫把他扔到了南极
is that she sent him to the South Pole.
回来的路很遥远
which is an awfully long walk..back.
除非会飞
if you can't fly.
所以  他来到水边
So..When he reached the water,
迅速潜入水中
he dived in through the dept so fast...
中午时他已抵达南汉普顿海域
that he was in Southampton waters by lunchtime.
在那儿搭两点半的船
And from there, he took the 2.30 to Weybridge,
然后在克拉珀姆换船
changed at Clapham Junction and
向一只路过的野鸭打听去白金汉宫的路
asked a passing mallard the way to Buckingham Palace.
他游过泰晤士河  从出水孔里钻出来
He swam up the Thames, out through the plughole,
让厨师
and gave the cook,
妈妈还有惠特克太太吃了一惊
Mama and ...Mrs Whittaker quite a shock.
女孩儿们听到了一片混乱
Now when the girls heard all the commotions,
她们跑进厨房给他彻底地洗了个澡
they ran to the kitchen where they gave him a good scrub,
并给了他一条马鲛鱼和一个吻
a mackerel and a kiss.
当她们吻他时
and as they kissed him,
猜他变成了什么
guess what he turned into?
一个英俊的王子
A handsome prince.
一只短尾巴的信天翁
A short-tailed Albatross.
有一双大翅膀
With wings so big
这样他就可以一把搂过他的两个女儿了
that he could wrap them both his two girls together.
好了  该睡觉了  快点
Now, now.. It's time for bed.Come on.
把这两匹小马拉回马厩
Take these horsies to stable.
-晚安  -晚安
- Good night.  - Good night.
喂食刷洗然后睡觉
Feed them, bath them and to bed.
辛普森夫人会参加吗
Will Mrs Simpson be there?
我哥哥坚持让她来
My brother's insisting.
他是认真的吗
Is he serious?
让她参加晚宴吗
About her coming to dinner?
不是  对她
No. About her!
一个有夫之妇  他不会的
A married woman? He can't be.
她会
She can.
对了
By the way,
我发现一个很有趣的人
I think I found someone rather interesting.
在哈里大街  一个医生
On Harley Street. A doctor.
绝不
Out of the question.
我不想再谈了  到此为止
I'm not having this conversation again. The matter's settled.
他的方法好像很特别
His approach seems rather different....
现在开始吗
Now?
开始
Now.
如今约克之子把我们讨厌的冬天
Now is the winter of our discontent,
变成了灿烂的夏天
Made glorious summer by this sun of York".
所有掠过我们家园的乌云
And all the clouds that lour'd upon our house
都被深埋在海洋的怀抱中
In the deep bosom of the ocean buried.
现在  我们的双眉周围缠绕着凯旋的花环
Now are our brows, bound with victorious... wreaths;
谢谢
Thank you!
发音不错  那谁
Lovely diction Mr...?
罗格  莱昂内尔・罗格
Logue. Lionel Logue.
罗格先生
Well, Mr.Logue.
我听不出这是一个丑陋的家伙
I'm not hearing the cries
想要成为国王的呐喊
of a deformed creature yearning to be King.
也看不出理查三世像殖民地的国王
Nor did I realize Richard the Third was King of the Colonies.
我知道所有台词  我演过这角色
I do know all the lines. I've played the role before.
-在悉尼吗  -珀斯
- Sydney?  - Perth.
剧场很多的城镇  对吧
Major theater town, is it?
很狂热
Enthusiastic.
我经过了层层筛选
I was well reviewed.
莱昂内尔
Yes... well...Lionel,
我们的戏剧社
I think our dramatic society,
想找个年轻点的
is looking for someone slightly younger and a...
更有帝王气质的人
little more regal.
得先关上外面那个  再把这个往前推
You have to shut that one first. Put that one forth.
很好
Excellent.
你在哪找到的这个医生
Where did you find this...physician?
分类广告
Classifieds,
紧挨着"法国模特  请联系牧羊菜市场"那条
next to 'French model, Shepherd's Market'.
有人强烈推荐他
He comes highly recommended.
为了救济穷人他收取高昂的费用
Charges substantial fees in order to help the poor.
天啊  或许他是共产主义者
Oh dear, perhaps he's a Bolshevik?!
没有前台  他喜欢简单
No receptionist. He likes to keep things simple.
我们是约翰逊夫妇
The Johnson's.
你可以进去了  约翰逊先生
You can go in now, Mr. Johnson.
莱昂内尔说
Lionel says...
如果你愿意可以在这等  约翰逊夫人
wait here if you wish, Mrs Johnson.
或者  天  天
Or, it being a p-
天不错  也  也许您可以去散步
pleasant day, p-perhaps take a stroll.
我说的对吗  莱昂内尔
Was that alright...Lionel?
棒极了  维利  等你妈妈来接你吧
Marvellous! Willy. You can stay and wait for your mom.
约翰逊夫人
Mrs Johnson...
约翰逊先生  您请进
Mr Johnson, Do you come in?
维利是个好孩子
He's a good lad, Willy.
第一次来见我时
He could hardly make a sound, you know,
他几乎一个音都发不出
when he first came to me.
我儿子们的杰作  不错吧
My boys made those. They are good, aren't they?
请随意
Please make yourself comfortable.
有人告诉我不要坐得太近
I was told not to sit too close.
我认为和王子说话时
Well I believe when speaking with a prince,
要等王子选话题
One waits for the prince to choose a topic.
让我开始谈话
Waiting for me to... commence
那得等很久
a conversation .. one can wait a rather long wait.
您知道什么笑话吗
Do you know any jokes?
计时不是我的强项
Timing isn't my strong suit.
喝茶吗
Cup of tea?
不  谢谢
No thank you.
我要来一杯
I think I'll have one.
罗格医生您还不开始治疗吗
Aren't you going to start treating me, Dr Logue?
除非您愿意被治疗
Only if you're interested in being treated.
请叫我莱昂内尔
Please, call me Lionel.
我更愿称你为先生
I prefer Doctor.
我更愿被称为莱昂内尔  我该怎么称呼您
I prefer Lionel. What'll I call you?
殿下  之后可以称阁下
Your Royal Highness, then Sir after that.
在这个场合太正式了  您的名字是
A little bit formal for here. I prefer names.
阿尔伯特・弗雷德里克・亚瑟・乔治王子
Prince Albert ...Frederick Arthur George.
叫博迪怎样
How about Bertie?
只有我的家人那么叫
Only my family uses that.
很好  在这里  我们平等相处比较好
Perfect. In here, it's better if we're equals.
如果我们真平等  我就不用来了
If we were equals, I wouldn't be here.
在家陪妻子
I'd be at home with my wife
谁管我结巴
and no one would give a damn.
请不要抽烟
Please, Don't do that.
什么
I'm sorry?
我认为抽烟对您的健康不利
I believe, sucking smoke into your lungs will kill you.
我的医生说这能放松喉咙
My physicians say it relaxes the throat.
一群白痴
They're idiots.
他们都是御医
They've all been knighted.
那就是官方认证的白痴
Makes it official then.
我的地盘我做主
My castle, my rules.
谢谢
Thank you.
请问你最早的记忆是
What was your earliest memory?
什  什么意思
What on earth do you mean?
你记得的第一件事
Your first recollection.
我不
I'm not...
不是来谈私事的
here to discuss my personal matters.
那您来干什么
Why're you here then?
因为我他妈的结巴
Because I am bloody well stammer!
您脾气挺大
You have a bit of a temper?
这是我缺点之一
One of my many faults.
结巴是从何时开始的
When did the defect start?
一直都这样
I've always been this way!
我觉得不是
I doubt that.
你知道什么  结巴的是我
Don't tell me! It's my stammer!
可我是专家
It's my field.
我向您保证  口吃绝非天生
I can assure you, no infant starts to speak with a stammer.
您是几岁开始的
When did yours start?
四五岁
Four or five.
一般都是这个年纪
That's typical.
都这么说
So I've been told.
我记事起就结巴了
I can't remember not doing it.
我知道
I can believe that.
您思考的时候也会停顿吗
Do you hesitate when you think?
胡说
Don't be ridiculous.
自言自语时呢
How about when you talk to yourself?
博迪  所有人都会偶尔自言自语
Everyone natters to themselves occasionally, Bertie.
别那么叫我
Stop calling me that.
我就这么叫
I'm not going to call you anything else.
那就别说了
Then we shan't speak!
医生  这次你收钱吗
Are you charging for this, Doctor?
收  一大笔呢
A fortune.
泡一会再喝
I'll just let that brew.
那么  自言自语时  你结巴吗
So, when you talk to yourself, do you stammer?
当然不会
Of course not!
那您的结巴还能治好
Well, that proves your impediment isn't a permanent part of you.
你觉得病因是什么
What do you think was the cause?
我不 不知道
I don't...Don't know.
也不  不在乎  我就是结巴
I don't care! I stammer!
没人能治好
And no one can fix it.
我打赌  您此时此刻就能流利地朗诵
I Bet you, you can read flawlessly, right here, right now.
要是我赢  我就要问您更多问题
And if I win the bet, I get to ask you more questions.
-如果我赢呢  -您不必回答
- And if I win? - You don't have to answer.
一般人都  都赌钱
One usually... wagers money.
每人一先令作为开始
A bob each to keep it sweet?
-你出一先令  -我不  不带钱
- Let's see your shilling?? - I don't... carry money.
就知道您没有
I had a funny feeling you mightn't.
我借您  下回还我
I'll stake you. And you can pay me back next time.
谁说有下回
Who says there is a next time?
那倒是  我还没决定给您治疗
I haven't agreed to take you on, yet.
请起立  看这个
Please stand. And take a look at that.
我读  读不了
I can't...can't read this.
您都没试就输给我一先令
Then you owe me a shilling, for not trying.
活着  还是死去  这...
To be... or not to be, that...
我读不了
I can't read!
还没完呢
I haven't finished yet.
我用这机器给您录音
I'm going to record your voice
再放出来给您听
and then play it back to you on the same machine.
这机器棒极了
This is brilliant.
美国的最新产品  银音牌
It's the latest thing from America: its a Silvertone.
戴上这个
Pop this on?
伙计  这能赚一先令  您可以满载而归
There's a bob in this, mate. You can go home rich!
-这在放音乐  -我知道
- You're playing music. - I know.
那我怎么听见自己说什么
How can I hear what I'm saying?
王子的脑子肯定知道嘴在说什么
Surely a Prince's brain knows what its mouth is doing.
你一定不了解王子
You're not well acquainted with Royal Princes, are you?
完全没用
Hopeless. Hopeless!
您读得非常好
You were sublime.
我怎么会为了一先令欺骗王子殿下
Would I lie to a prince of the realm to win twelve pence?
我怎么知道一个澳洲人
I've no idea what an Australian might do
为了那点钱会做出什么
for that sort of money.
我放出来给您听听
Let me play it back to you.
不用
No.
那好吧  我就要提问了
All right then, I get to ask you the question.
谢谢你  医生
Thank you, Doctor,
我觉得这治不好我
I don't feel.. this is for me.
麻烦你了  再见
Thank You for your time, Bye.
阁下
Sir?
录音是免费的
The recording is free.
请收下做纪念
Please keep it as a souvenir.
没用
No.
乔治五世
1934年圣诞讲话
诺福克郡  桑德林姆宫
当前形势下
For the present,
我们共同担当的重任
the work to which we are all equally bound,
便是在全国之内
is to arrive at a reasoned tranquillity
营造和平平静的环境
within our borders,
在此萧条期间
to regain prosperity at this time of depression
摒弃私心
without self-seeking
与我们这些为之前的重负倍感灰心与挫折的人
and to carry with us those whom the burden of past years
再图繁荣
has disheartened or overborne.
祝每位国民圣诞快乐
To all, to each, I wish a Happy Christmas.
上帝保佑你们
God bless you.
直播结束
And off air.
熟能生巧
Easy when you know how.
阁下
Sir.
你来试试
Have a go yourself.
-演讲很成功  陛下  -伍德先生
- Congratulations, Sir. - Mr. Wood.
他很厉害
Splendid fellow.
教会我最重要的一条
Chap taught me everything I know:
麦克风自然会播音
let the microphone do the work.
-谢谢  -各位这边走
- Thank you. - Gentlemen.
挺胸坐直
Sit up, straight back,
抬头面对话筒  直视它
face boldly up to the bloody thing and stare it square in the eye
当它是个平民
as you would any decent Englishman.
拿出皇家气派
Show who's in command.
爸爸  我觉得我读不了
Papa, I don't think I can read this.
如果读不了  这该死的东西能毁了一切
This devilish device will change everything if you don't.
过去一个国王要做的事情
In the past all a King had to do was
就是穿上正装摆摆样子别掉下马
look respectable in uniform and not fall off his horse.
现在我们必须进入平常百姓家
Now we must invade people's homes
去讨好他们
and ingratiate ourselves with them.
所谓皇室家族
This family has been reduced
已经降为最低等的平民
to those lowest, basest of all creatures.
我们变成了演员
We've become actors!
我们不是皇室  而是公司
We're not a family, we're a firm.
然而某些成员随时会失业
Yet at any moment, some of us may be out of work.
你的兄长  我的王储
Your darling brother, and future king!
他唯一感兴趣的妻子
The only wife he appears interested in
无一例外都是有夫之妇
is invariably the wife of another!
他和弗勒斯女士分手了
He's broken off with Lady Furness.
又看上了辛普森夫人
And taken up a Mrs. Simpson,
一个已经结过两次婚的女人
a woman with two husbands living!
我跟他直说
I told him straight,
皇室不会接受这种女人
no divorced person could ever be received at court.
他说  他感到十分幸福
He said, "It made him sublimely happy."
我想这是因为她已经和他上床了
I imagined that was because she was sleeping with him.
他说  "我保证"
"I give you my word..." this is what he said.
"我们绝没发生不正当关系"
"I give you my word we've never had immoral relations,"
当着他父亲的面撒谎
stared square into his father's face... and lied!
等我死了  他用不了一年
When I'm dead that boy will ruin himself,
就会毁掉自己  毁掉这个家族  毁掉这个国家
this family, and this nation, within twelve months.
到时谁收拾残局
Who'll pick up the pieces?
希特勒震慑了半个欧洲
Herr Hitler, intimidating half of Europe,
另半个在马歇尔・斯大林掌控
Marshall Stalin the other half.
谁来保护英国
Who'll stand between us,
免遭纳粹军队和无产阶级的侵犯
the jackboots, and the proletarian abyss?
你能行吗
You?
你哥哥逃避责任
With your older brother shirking his duties,
你势必将更多地做这事情
you're going to have to do a lot more of this.
你自己来一次
Have a go yourself.
-通过无线电  -别紧张  孩子
- With the wireless... - Get it out, boy!
-这一伟大的  现  -现代
- ...one of the m-marvels of m... - Modern...
慢慢来  小心组词
Just take your time, form your words carefully.
-现代科技  我能够  -放松
- ...science, I am enabled, to... - Relax!
-大胆说  -在这个圣诞节
- Just try it! - This Chrismas Day...
向我的国...
...to speak to all my...
说啊
Do it!
骗人的混蛋
Lying .. bastard.
-这在放音乐  -我知道
- You're playing music. - I know.
我怎么知道自己说什么
How can I hear what I'm saying?
王子的大脑肯定知道嘴在说什么
Surely a Prince's brain knows what its mouth is doing?
你不了解王子
You're not well acquainted with Royal Princes, are you?
活着  还是死去  这是个难题
To be, or not to be, that is the question:
哪一种选择更为高贵
whether 'tis nobler in the mind
是甘心忍受残暴命运的飞箭流石
to suffer the slings and arrows of outrageous fortune,
还是奋起搏击无边的苦海
or to take arms against a sea of troubles,
通过反抗一了百了
and by opposing end them.
死去  睡去  仅此而已
To die; to sleep; no more.
如果说睡去能了结
and by a sleep to say we end
肉体注定要承受的伤心
the heart-ache and the thousand natural shocks
以及千百次的打击  那可是...
that flesh is heir to. 'Tis a consummation...
完全没用
Hopeless. Hopeless!
只能治病
Strictly business.
别打听私  私事
No p...personal nonsense.
我想在之前的会面我已经说清楚了
I thought I'd made that very clear in our interview.
欠我那一先令带了吗
Have you got the shilling you owe me?
没带
No, I haven't.
没想到
Didn't think so.
而且上次你耍花招了
Besides, you tricked me!
身体操练和花招很重要
Physical excercises and tricks are important...
你们的要求
What you're asking
只能治标不治本
will only deal with the surface of the problem.
那不是更有效吗
Is that effecient?
在我看来
No, as far as I see it,
我丈夫只是在演讲时有身体上的困难
my husband has mechanical difficulties with his speech.
也许处理这个就可以了
Maybe just deal with that.
-我愿意刻苦练习  罗格医生  -叫我莱昂内尔
- I'm willing to work hard, Doctor Logue... - Lionel.
你愿意治我吗
Are you...are you willing to do your part?
行  你想治身体对吧
Alright. You want mechanics?
我要放松你的颚肌
We need to relax your jaw muscles
练习绕口令  锻炼舌头
and strengthen your tongue by repeating tongue twisters
比如说  四是四  十是十
For example, I am a thistle-sifter.
十四是十四
I have a sieve of sifted thistles and
四十是四十
a sieve of unsifted thistles because I am a thistle-sifter.
行
Fine!
你的腹肌比较松软
You have a flabby tummy,
我们要花时间增强你的横膈膜力量
we need spend some times to strength in your diaphragm.
很简单的物理治疗
Simple mechanics.
我们就需要这个
That is all we ask.
那我只收一先令就够了
And that's about a shilling's worth.
别提他妈的先令
Forget about the bloody shilling!
我可能时不时地
Perhaps, upon occasions,
需要你帮  帮忙
you might be requested to assist
应付些活动
in coping with some minor event.
-你同意吗  -当然
- Will that agreeable? - Of course.
好  您的任务就这些
Yes. And that will be the full extent of your services.
那下周见
Shall I see you next week?
我们得天天见
I shall see you every day.
感觉下巴放松
Feel the loosening of the jaw.
好  来蹦两下  蹦  放松肩膀
Good. Little bounces, bounces. Shoulders loose.
来  甩嘴唇
Now lips.
深吸一口气  扩张胸腔
Take a nice deep breath. Expand your chest..
把手放在肋骨上
put your hands on your ribs.
继续吸  好
Deeper, good.
-感觉如何  -满腹废话
- How do you feel? - Full of hot air.
演说不就是这样吗
Isn't that what public speaking is all about?
我妻子和我很荣幸来参观如此重要的
My wife and I are glad to visit this important...
深深吸气  把殿下顶起来
Take a good deep breath, and up comes Her Royal Highness
慢慢呼气  把殿下放下
and slowly exhale, and down comes Her Royal Highness.
-博迪你还好吗  -好
- You alright, Bertie? - Yes.
这还挺好玩
This is actually quite good fun.
-母...母亲  -每次都加快  母亲
- Mmm...mother.  - Shorter time each time. Mmm...mother.
-模  模范工业产区  -再吸气
- Mmm...manufactoring district. - Another deep breathe...
-吃葡萄  -吃葡萄
- Jack and Jill... - Jack and Jill...
-不吐葡萄皮  -不吐葡萄皮
- ...went up the hill. - ...went up the hill.
现在前后摆动
Now just sway.
很好
Perfect.
我们不  不愿
We'll not permit us to...
-放松肩膀  -打南边来了个喇嘛
- Loosen the shoulders. - Ding dong bell,
手里提着五斤鳎犸  打北边来了个哑巴
which is in the well... who put any little ton in ten...
还不长记性  博迪  继续
Still short memory, Bertie, come on.
-翁  翁  -王  王
-A cow. A cow. - A king. A king.
只要能站在窗前掉嗓
Anyone who can shout vows in a open window
就能学会演讲
can learn to deliver a speech.
40秒  50秒
Fourty... fifty!
-深深吸气  -今天
- Take a deep breath, and... - It is...
-然后脱口而出  -狗屁御医都他妈没用
- Let the words flow. - Knight as a bloody wack...
再来一次博迪  加油
Come on. One more time, Bertie, do it!
十四是十四
...a sieve of sifted thistles...
-父亲  父亲  -父...父亲  父亲
- Father. Father. - F...Father. Father.
-唇齿音  父  -父亲  父亲  父亲
- Name of the "th", father. - Father. F...Father. Father.
桑德林姆宫
1936年
-博迪  -大卫
- Hello, Bertie. - Hello David.
-你怎么站在外面  -没事
- How did you come out. - Not at all.
等很久了吗
You waiting long?
老天  真他妈冷
Christ, it's bloody freezing.
你怎么样
Where've you been?
-到处忙  -我也是
- I've Been busy. - So was I.
伊丽莎白得了肺炎
Elizabeth has pneumonia.
真可怜  她会康复的
I'm sorry. She'll recover.
父亲就难说了
Father won't.
我开车
I'll drive.
-老家伙这是成心的  -成心要死吗
- Old bugger's doing this on purpose. - Dying?
提前离席
Departing prematurely...
恶化和威利斯(辛普森夫人)的关系
to complicate matters with Wallis.
得了吧  大卫  他都病这么久了
For heaven's sake, David. You know how long he's been ill.
威利斯是这么想的
Wallis explained.
她对这种事很明白
She's terribly clever about these things.
1912年6月11日于威斯敏斯特
... whereas by letters patent under the Great Seal,
上诏加盖国玺
bearing date of Westminster, the eleventh June, 1912
乔治五世陛下宣布
His Majesty King George V did constitute,
任命国家议会
order and declare that there should be a guardian,
-监国  -我  我不明白
- ...Custos Regni... - I-I cannot...I'm confused.
-代天巡守  -我不懂你在说什么
- in the form of council of state. - I don't understand what you are talking about...
阁下  这是有关英国议会的决议
It's the order of the Council for the State, Sir.
授权我们代您行政
So we may act on your behalf.
说  说清楚点  我
...talk clearer to me, I'm afraid...
-我一点都不明白  -通过
- I'm so confused but...- Approved.
谢谢
Thank you.
阁下  请伸手
Give me your hand, sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
感觉好点吗  阁下
Feeling a little better, Sir?
没有  不好  太难受了
No. I'm not feeling any better. I feel dreadful.
你滑冰  滑冰去了吗
Been ice skating? ...Ice skating.
没有  乔治
No, no, George.
是  是  他好着呢
Yes, yes, he's alright, of course.
亲爱的我知道  即使聊再长时间
I know, darling, a talk, even a lovely long talk,
也比不上拥抱和小醉
is a poor substitute for holding tight and making drowsy.
我们也不能小醉了
Nor making our own drowsies either,
因为最近酒会太多
as we've had to do far too often lately.
大卫  来吃晚饭
David, dinner?
我跟威利斯说话呢
I'm on with Wallis!
是博迪  不  不  这无所谓
Bertie. No. No, it's not important.
我不想当国王  真的
I don't want to! No!
晚点打给你  再见
I'll phone you later. Bye.
威利斯很想我
Wallis misses me terribly.
妈妈说你晚饭迟到了
Mama says you're late for dinner.
她忘了
She forgets
爸爸的钟都快半小时
Papa's bloody clocks were always half an hour fast.
陛下怎样  他没在痛吧
How is the King? I hope he is not in pain.
没有  阁下  陛下现在平静多了
No, no, sir. His Majesty is quieter now.
谢谢
Thank you.
大卫  你父王要在场
David, if your father were here,
不会容忍你迟到
tardiness would not be tolerated.
也不会容忍这样不愉快的事情发生
None of this unpleasantness would be tolerated.
殿下  如您所知  我很欣赏您
You know sir, I appreciate that
您与令尊相比
you are different from your father
目光远大  性格温和
both in outlook and temperament.
我想告诉您
I want you to know that
只要国王质疑您的行为
whenever the King questioned your conduct,
我都是站在您的立场上
I tried in your interest,
为您的利益着想
to present it in a most favourable light.
我相信您心里时刻想着'国王'的利益
I can always trust you to have my best interests at heart.
恐怕国王大限将至
I fear, our vigil will not be of long duration.
各位请慢用
Please continue.
我们将乔治弟兄
We commend our brother George
交予仁慈的天父  我们的造物主和救赎者
to the mercy of God, our Maker and Redeemer.
国王万岁
Long live the King.
我希望  我能做得和他一样好
I hope, I will make good as he has made good.
这到底是谁怎么了
What on earth was that?
可怜的威利斯  这下我陷入困境了
Poor Wallis. Now I'm trapped!
来段莎士比亚的戏吧  爸爸
Time for a Shake, dad?
真的要吗
You sure?
来吧
Go on.
准备好猜谜
Put your thinking caps on.
我猜是《麦克白》
Bet its the Scottish Play.
不对  肯定《奥赛罗》  总是《奥赛罗》
No, I bet it's Othello. It's always Othello.
你害怕吗  不要怕
Are thou afeard. Be not afeard.
凯列班[莎士比亚剧《暴风雨》中角色]
Caliban!
老天  肯定是蒙对的
Oh! For heaven's sake.. that was a lucky guess!
别听那书呆子的  继续  爸爸
Don't listen to egghead. Go on, Dad.
岛上回响着各种声音  空气宜人
The isle is full of noises, sounds and sweet airs,
讨人喜欢  没有伤害
that give delight, and hurt not.
有时无数叮咚乐器声
Sometimes a thousand
在我耳边鸣响
twanging instruments Will hum about mine ears;
有时我酣睡醒来
and sometimes voices, that, if then
听见歌声  又使我沉沉睡去
I had waked after long sleep will make me sleep again:
好了  小机灵鬼  下一句是什么
Alright, clever clogs, what comes next?
于是在梦里  我以为云要散了
And then, in dreaming, the clouds methought would open,
昭示财富将临  醒来之后
and show riches ready to drop upon me; that when I'm awake...
醒来之后  我含泪重又入梦
...when I waked, I cried to dream again.
这可真悲痛
It's such a sad thought.
肯定是我的下一个病人来早了
My next patient must be early.
你们得走了  小伙子们  对不起
You better go lads, I'm sorry.
马上来  克利福德
Won't be a moment, Clifford.
博迪  他们告诉我说你不来了
Bertie! They told me not to expect you.
节哀顺变
I am sorry about your father.
希望没有打扰您
I don't wish to intrude..
没有没有  请进
Oh no... Please come in.
我一直在练习  无论如何每天练一小时
I've been practising. One hour a day. In spite of everything.
你那儿怎么了
What's going on there?
不好意思  我在跟孩子们胡闹
I was, sorry, mucking around with my kids.
你今天想进行练习吗
Do you feel like working today?
柯蒂斯双翼飞机
A Curtis bi-plane.
我来准备点热牛奶
I'll put on some hot milk.
罗格  我喝点刺激的
Logue, I'd kill for something stronger.
我父亲临终前我不在  这让我抱憾至今
I wasn't there for my father's death. Still makes me sad.
我可以想象
I can imagine so.
你父亲是干什么的
What did you father do?
他是个酿酒的
He was a brewer.
至少喝酒不要钱
At least there was free beer.
这杯来缅怀您父亲
Here's to the memory of your father.
后来  他们告诉我
I was informed, after the fact...
我父亲的临终遗言是
that my father's last words were:
博迪比其他几个兄弟加一起更勇敢
Bertie has more guts than the rest of his brothers put together.
他没能直接对我说
He couldn't say that to my face.
我哥哥
My brother.
他怎么了
What about him?
试着唱出来
Try singing it.
什么
I'm sorry.
你会唱什么歌
What songs do you know?
唱歌
Songs?
对  唱歌
Yes songs.
《史瓦尼河》
"Swanee River"?
我喜欢那首歌
I love that song.
刚好也是我的最爱
Happens to be my favorite.
给我唱唱副歌部分
Sing me the chorus.
不  绝对不行
No. Certainly not.
我以前总想做模型  父亲不让
Always wanted to build models. Father wouldn't allow it.
他集邮  所以我们都得跟着集邮
He collected stamps. So we had to collect stamps.
如果您唱歌  就可以把这个做完
You can finish that off. If you sing.
我可不想在这瞎哼哼
I'm not going to sit here, wobbling.
你可以跟着我唱
You can with me.
因为你是个怪人
Because you're peculiar.
我就当你在夸我
I take that as a compliment.
按规矩来
Rules are rules.
我才不哼《史瓦尼河》
I'm not crooning "Swanee River".
那唱《康城赛马》
"Camptown Races" then.
我哥哥大卫告诉我  嘟哒
My brother David, he said to me, doo- dah
嘟哒  持续发音可以让您说话流利
doo-dah... Continuous sound will give you flow.
现在大卫当国王了  会不会感觉很奇怪
Does it feel strange, now that David's on the throne?
说实话
To tell the truth,
这是种解脱
it was a relief...
知道自己当不了国王
knowing I wouldn't be King.
可除非他有孩子  否则您就是下一任
But unless he produces an heir, you're next in line.
然后是您的女儿伊丽莎白继任
And your daughter, Elizabeth, would then succeed you.
医生啊医生  你是在胡说
You're barking up the wrong tree now, Doctor, Doctor.
叫我莱昂内尔  看  你不结巴了
Lionel See? You didn'stammer.
我当然不结巴  我在唱歌
Of course I didn't stammer, I was singing!
作为奖励
Well, as a little reward,
您可以在支架上抹点胶水
you get to put some glue on these struts.
你儿子不会介意吧
Your boy, won't mind?
不  完全不会
No, not at all.
大卫和我曾经很亲密  你知道  年轻人嘛
David and I were very close. Young bucks... You know.
你们追一个姑娘
Did you chase the same girls?
安排引见的时候大卫总是很帮得上忙
David was always very helpful in arranging introductions.
我们都受到了巴黎的Paulette的无微不至的照顾
We shared the expert ministrations of Paulette in Paris.
当然不是同一个时候
Not at the same time of course.
David嘲笑过你吗
Did David ever tease you?
他们都嘲笑过  Buh-buh-buh-博迪
Yes, they all did. Buh-buh-buh-Bertie?
父亲纵容他们  "别紧张
Father encouraged it. "Get it out,
孩子"  说这样能让我不结巴
boy!" Said it would make me stop.
他说"我害怕我父亲
Said that "I sas afraid of my father,
我的孩子必须也得怕我"
and my children are damn well going to be afraid of me."
你天生就是右撇子吗
Are you naturally right handed?
左撇子  我被迫改过来的  现在我习惯右手了
Left. I was punished. Now I use the right.
没错  这种情况在结巴中很常见
Yes, that's very common with stammerers.
还做过别的矫正吗
Anything other corrections?
X型腿
Knock knees.
从早到晚都得戴着金属夹板
Metal splints were made...worn night and day.
那一定很疼
That must have been painful.
疼死了  现在腿直了
Bloody agony. Straight legs now.
你同哪个家人最亲近
Who were you closest to in your family?
乳母  不是第一个  她喜欢大卫  讨厌我
Nannies. Not my first nanny, though..She loved David...hated me.
我们被带去
When we are presented to my
觐见父母的时候  她掐我
parents for the daily viewing, she'd pinch me..
我就哭  然后被立刻
I'd cry and be handed back to her..
交回给她
immediately.
然后  她就
Then... she would...
唱出来
Sing it.
"然后她就不喂我"
"Then she wouldn't feed me, far far away."
三年之后我父母才发现
Took my parents three years to notice.
胃会出毛病一点都不奇怪  直到现在
As you can imagine, it caused some stomach problems. Still.
你弟弟约翰尼呢
What about your brother Johnny?
你和他亲近吗
Were you close to him?
约翰尼  好孩子
Johnny.. Sweet boy.
得了癫痫
Epilepsy...and...
他不一样
he was different.
13岁就去世了  不在公开场合出现
Died at 13, hidden from view.
他们告诉我这病不传染
I've been told it's not catching.
再来一杯吗
Do you want a top-up?
谢谢
Please.
莱昂内尔  你是第一个英国平民
You know, Lionel, you're the first ordinary Englishman...
澳大利亚平民
Australian.
同我真正交谈的
...I've ever really spoken to.
有时候  当我穿过街道  看见
Sometimes, when I ride through the streets and see, you know,
那些平民盯着我
the common man staring at me,
我总为我对他的生活一无所知
I'm struck by how little I know of his life,
和他对我的生活一无所知而感到震惊
and how little he knows of mine.
谢谢
Thank you.
朋友就是倾诉对象
What're friends for.
我本来不会明白
I wouldn't know.
巴尔莫勒尔堡  苏格兰
-够了亲爱的  -我得接着练
- That's enough darling. - I have to keep doing this.
百年的橡树  为了开阔视野就这么砍了
One hundred year old oaks...removed to improve the view!
她以为她是谁
Who does she think she is!
不管怎样  我们必须对辛普森夫人礼貌
Nonetheless...we must try to be pleasant towards Mrs Simpson.
你知道她管我叫"苏格兰胖厨子"吗
You know she calls me the Fat Scottish Cook?
你又不胖
You're not fat.
我快要发福了
I'm getting plump.
你不下厨
You seldom cook.
吃葡萄
I sifted seven.
闭嘴
Shut up!!
约克郡公爵与公爵夫人殿下驾到
Their Royal Highnesses the Duke and Duchess of York.
见到你们俩真高兴
How lovely to see you both.
欢迎来到我们的乡间小屋
Welcome to our little country shack.
国王邀请我才来的
I came at the invitation of the King.
国王陛下
Your Majesty.
抱歉我们来晚了
Sorry we're late.
很高兴见到你  辛普森夫人
Very nice to see you, Mrs. Simpson.
很高兴
Very nice.
大卫
Hello David.
我发现你改造了花园
You're making some changes to the garden, I see.
对  还没弄完
Yes, I am. I am not quite finished.
别告诉我我表现不礼貌  丘吉尔先生
Don't tell me I behaved badly, Mr Churchill.
恰恰相反  殿下  礼仪规定
On the contrary, your Royal Highness. Etiquette decrees
皇室成员应当被正式主人接待  在此  就应该是国王
royalty must be greeted by the official host: in this case: the King.
-而不是平民  -谢谢
- Not a commoner. - Thank you.
她是怎么迷住他的
What is her hold on him?
不知道
I have no idea.
显然她在上海国教教会
Apparently she has certain...skills,
学会了某些技巧
acquired in an establishment in Shanghai.
-大卫  -马上  亲爱的
- David.  - Just be a sec, darling.
大卫  我一直想见你
David, I've been trying to see you...
我忙得很
I've been terribly busy.
忙什么
Doing what?
当国王
Kinging.
Kinging
如今需要如履薄冰
is a precarious business these days.
俄罗斯的沙皇何在  德国的威廉皇帝何在
Where is the Russian Tsar? Where is Cousin Wilhelm?
你可真无趣
You're being dreary.
难道当国王要把桑德林汉姆夏宫80个臣属革职
Is Kinging laying off eighty staff at Sandringham
给威利斯买更多的珍珠
and buying yet more pearls for Wallis while
而此时共产主义者以席卷了整个欧洲大陆
there are people marching across Europe singing the Red Flag?
你别操心了  希特勒先生会解决这些
Stop your worrying. Herr Hitler will sort that lot out.
那谁来解决希特勒先生
Who'll sort out Herr Hitler?
那瓶该死的二三年陈酿在哪
Where's the bloody '23?
你甚至让那女人住进妈妈的套房
And you've put that woman into our mother's suite?
妈妈没睡  不是吗
Mother's not still in the bed, is she?
这不好笑
That's not funny.
威利斯只喜欢最好的
Wallis likes the very best.
我不关心你晚上跟哪个女人暧昧
I don't care what woman you carry on with at night,
只要你白天履行身为国王的职责
as long as you show up for duty in the morning!
威利斯不只是跟我暧昧
Wallis is not just some woman I am carrying on with.
我们准备结婚了
We intend to marry.
你说什么
Excuse me?
她正在申请离婚
She's filing a petition for divorce.
老天
Good God.
你就不能给她间好房子  再给她封个爵位吗
Can't you just give her a nice house and a title?
我不会让她做我的情妇的
I won't have her as my mistress.
大卫  教会不允许离婚
David, the Church does not recognise divorce
而你正是教会的领袖
and you are the head of the Church.
我难道一点权利也没有吗
Haven't I any rights?
你有很多特权
Many privileges...
不是一回事
Not the same thing.
那些平民都能为了爱情结婚
Your beloved common man may marry for love,
我怎么就不行
why not me?
你要是平民
If you were the common man,
又凭什么加冕为王
on what basis could you possibly claim to be King?!
听起来你对我们这悲惨的宪法很有研究
Sounds like you've studied our wretched constitution.
听起来你没研究
Sounds like you haven't.
这就是你的目的吗
Is that what this is all about?
从演讲课开始  反复练习
Brushing up.. hence the elocution lessons?
我是想
I'm trying to t-t...
想再多些听众吗  博  博  博迪
Yearning for a larger audience are we, B-b-b-bertie?
别
D-don't ...
弟弟想把哥哥赶下王位
Younger brother trying to push older brother off throne..
还  还  还真老套
Pa pa.. ...Positively medieval.
-你上哪儿去了这么久  -你跟谁聊天呢
- Where have you been all this time? - Who have you been talking to?
不关你的是
Never you mind.
你可真是个让人又爱又恨小家伙
Ahh..What a complicated lovely coon you are.
你喜欢就好
I try to be.
所有的努力都尽付东流了
All that work, down the drain.
我亲生的哥哥
My own brother...
我居然  居然对着他一个字都说不出来
I couldn't say.. I couldn't say a word to him in reply!
为什么你跟大卫说话比跟我说话结巴得多
Why do you stammer more with David than you do with me?
因为你收了一大笔钱听我说话
Because you're bloody well paid to listen!
博迪  我可不是陪聊的艺伎
Bertie, I'm not a geisha girl.
别说俏皮话了
Stop trying to be so bloody clever!
大卫怎么回事  会让你说不出话的
What is it about David that stops you speaking?
你是怎么回事  他妈成天
What is it about you, that bloody
没完没了纠结这个问题
well makes you want to go on about it, the whole bloody time.
粗鄙却很流利  你骂人的时候从不结巴
Vulgar but fluent. You don't stammer when you swear.
滚蛋
Bugger off!
你只会骂这个吗
Is that the best you can do?
去你妈的  你这禽兽不如的混蛋
Well, bloody bugger to you, you beastly bastard.
公共学校的道学先生都比你会骂人
A public school prig can do better than that.
日
Shit!
日  日  日  日
Shit, shit, shit! Shit!
看脏话从舌尖喷涌而出
See how defecation flows trippingly from the tongue?
因为我生气了
Because I'm angry!
你会说那个F开头的词吗
You Know the f-word?
通奸
Fornication?
不是吧  博迪
Oh Bertie.
操  操  操  操
Fuck. Fuck, fuck, fuck!
没错  你看  多流利
Yes! You see! Not a hesitation!
见鬼  见鬼  日  日
Bloody, bloody, bloody! Shit, shit,
日  混蛋  混蛋  操  操  奶子
Shit! Bugger, bugger, bugger! Fuck, fuck, fuck! Tits.
爸  怎么了
Dad? What's going on?
抱歉  做作业去
Sorry. Finish your homework
我们很少见到你这一面
Well ..That's a side of you we don't get to see that often.
我们不该这样的  不能公开这样
No. No we're not supposed to really, not publicly.
出去透透气吧
Let's get some air.
不  罗格  我认为这不是个好主意
No Logue, I don't think that's a good idea.
怎么了  什么让你这么沮丧
What's the matter? What's got you so upset?
罗格  说出来吓到你
Logue, you have no idea.
我哥哥迷恋一个结过两次婚的女人
My brother is infatuated with a woman who's been married twice.
她正在申请离婚  而大卫决定要娶她
She's asking for a divorce and David is determined to marry her.
巴尔的摩的威利斯・辛普森夫人
Mrs Wallis Simpson of Baltimore.
这也没什么  以后就是巴尔的摩的威利斯皇后
That's all right. Queen Wallis of Baltimore?
难以想象
Unthinkable.
他能这么做吗
Can he do that?
当然不能  但他决意如此
Absolutely not. But he's going to anyway.
所有事情全乱套了
All hell's broken loose.
他们不能偷偷的继续吗
Can't they carry on privately?
要是他们愿意就好了
If only they would.
你的立场是什么
Where does that leave you?
我知道我的本份
I know my place!
我会尽我一切所能
I'll do anything...
让我哥哥继续留在王位上
in my power to keep my brother on the throne.
你是认真的
Is it that serious?
也许做国王是你的本份
Your place may be on the throne.
我不是我哥哥的替代者
I am not an alternative to my brother.
如果你是国王  你会做的比大卫更好
If you had to you could outshine David...
别乱说
Don't talk about this!
这近乎叛国
That's bordering on treason.
我只是说你可以做国王  你能做到
I'm just saying you could be King. You could do it!
这是叛国
That is treason!
我只是想让你明白
I'm trying to get you to realise
你不用被恐惧控制
you need not be governed by fear.
够了
I've had enough of this!
你到底在怕什么
What're you so afraid of?
你这些讨厌的话
Your poisonous words!
那你为什么来找我
Why'd you come to me?
你可不是什么中产阶级人士
You are not some middle class bugger,
上了演讲课去跟别人胡扯
who needs elocution lessons so you can chit-chat...
别对我的事指手画脚
Don't instruct me on my duties!
我是国王的儿子
I'm the son of a .... King...
国王的弟弟
the brother of a king.
你只是酿酒师没出息的儿子
You're the disappointing son of a brewer!
一个澳洲乡下来的暴发户
A jumped-up jackeroo from the outback!
你什么都不是
You're nobody.
疗程结束
These sessions are over!
花园入口  总统办公室  唐宁街十号
不是因为她是美国人  那不算什么
It's not because she's an American. That is the least of it.
是因为她是一个就要离婚两次的美国人
It's because she is a soon to be a twice divorced American,
而国王作为英国国教的最高领袖
and the King as head of The Church of England...
不能娶一个离过婚的女人
can not marry a divorced woman.
阁下  我对此感到遗憾
And Sir, I apologize for the nature of this,
根据苏格兰场的调查
according to Scotland Yard,
国王并不是辛普森夫人唯一爱人
the King has not always possess exclusive..Rights to Mrs. Simpson's... favours and affections,
她另有一个情人是个二手汽车商人  名叫推车盖
sharing them with a married used car salesman, a certain Mr Guy Trundle.
而且  还有传言说
In addition, it is also rumoured...
希特勒的大使  坎特・冯・李宾特洛普
Hitler's ambassador, Count von Ribbentrop,
每天给她送十七支康乃馨
sends her 17 carnations every day.
如果你哥哥继续无视内阁的忠告
Should your brother continue to
他必须逊位
ignore the advice of His Government, He must abdicate.
否则内阁别无选择只能辞职
Otherwise His Government has no choice but to resign.
首相
Prime Minister,
你要让这个国家没有内阁
you'd leave the country without a government?
一个国王该做他想做的
Does the King do what he wants,
还是该做他的人民想让他做的
or does he do what his people expect him to do?
怎么了  亲爱的
What's the matter, love?
我只是为一个病人苦恼
I'm Just having trouble with a patient.
这可不像你  怎么了
That isn't like you.. Why?
他很害怕  害怕他自己的影子
He's scared... He is afraid with his own shadow.
他们不就是为了这个来找你吗
Isn't that why they come to you?
这个人真的可以成就伟业
This fellow could be really somebody great,
但他反对我的说法
and he's fighting me.
可能他不想成就伟业
Perhaps, he doesn't want to be great.
可能那是你一厢情愿
Perhaps that's what you want.
我可能僭越了
I might have overstepped the mark.
去道歉
Apologize,
对你们两都好
do you both good.
很抱歉  罗格先生  公爵大人很忙
I'm very sorry, Mr Logue, the Duke is busy.
我可以等  或者晚点再来
I'm happy to wait. Or I could come back later.
我说了  公爵大人非常忙
As I said, the Duke is terribly busy.
谢谢
Thank you.
议会不会支持这桩婚姻的
The parliament will not support their marriage.
但还有其他原因  阁下
But there were other reasons for concern, Sir.
他不关心国家政策
He was careless with state papers.
他不承担义务  缺少决心
He lacked commitment and resolve.
还有人担心
There were those that worried
如果同德国开战  他是什么立场
where he would stand when war comes with Germany .
我们不会走到那一步吧
We're not coming to that?
绝对会  阁下
Indeed we are, Sir.
鲍德温首相否认这点
Prime Minister Baldwin may deny this,
但希特勒的野心昭然若揭
but Hitler's intent is crystal clear.
与德国大战在即
War with Germany will come,
而我们需要一个带领我们团结一致的国王
and we will need a King behind whom we can all stand united.
我担心  此时我哥哥
I fear...my brother is not of
还没有看清形势
sound mind, at this time.
你想过赋予自己什么头衔吗
Have you thought what you will call yourself?
当然不能是阿尔伯特  阁下  太德国化了
Certainly not Albert, Sir. Too Germanic.
乔治怎么样
What about George?
用你父亲的头衔  乔治六世
After your father? George the sixth.
是个不错的传承  你不觉得吗
It has rather a nice continuity to it, don't you think?
大卫  谢天谢地
David! Thank God.
你看起来很累
You look exhausted!
你还撑得住吗
How are you bearing up?
博迪  我已经决定了
Bertie. The decision's been made.
我要逊位
I am going.
我无法接受
I cannot accept that.
你无论如何都不该做此决定
You are in no condition to make that decision.
恐怕没有别的办法
I'm afraid there's no other way.
我要娶她
I must marry her.
我已经决定了  抱歉
My mind's made up. I'm... sorry.
真是个糟糕的消息
That's a terrible thing to hear.
大卫  没人想你这么做  特别是我
David, nobody wants that. I least of all.
终于  我可以说我自己要说的话
" At long last I am able to say, a few words of my own.
我于1936年12月10日签字证明
爱德华签署于景观台城堡
我从来没有想要隐瞒什么  但今天之前
I have never wanted to withhold anything, but until now,
根据宪法我不能发表任何讲话
it has not been constitutionally possible for me to speak.
几个小时之前  我卸下了
A few hours ago I discharged my last duty
作为一个国王和君主最后职责
as King and Emperor.
现在  将由我的弟弟约克公爵继位
Now that I have been succeeded by my brother, the Duke of York
首先我表明对他效忠
my first words must be to declare my allegiance to him.
全心全意忠顺
This I do with all my heart.
相信你们都知道
You all know the reasons
我宣布放弃王位的原因
which have impelled me to renounce the throne.
但是请你们相信我接下来的话
But you must believe me, when I tell you
如果没有我心爱女人的支持
I have found it impossible to carry the
我无法承担如此重任
heavy burden of responsibility and to discharge my duties..
也无法如我所愿的
as King as I would wish to do
卸除作为国王的职责
without the help and support of the woman I love...
同时  我希望你们知道
And I want you to know.
出于对我弟弟的了解
..This decision has been made less difficult to me
这个决定做的并不艰难
by the sure knowledge that my brother,
我弟弟一直致力于国家事务管理
with his long training in the public affairs of this country...
加上他的优秀品质
...and with his fine qualities...
必然能够即刻继位
...will be able to take my place forth with
不会让国家的前途和发展
without interruption or
受到任何的阻碍或伤害
injury to the life and progress of the empire."
登基会议  圣詹姆斯宫  1936年12月21日
我 在今天
I meet you at today...
在此情况下  和你们会面
in circumstances which are -
我保证你们会喜欢的
I'm sure you will love it.
谢谢宝贝  马鞍给我  玛格丽特
Thank you darling, saddles, Margret.
-好的  妈妈  -乖孩子
- Yes mom. - Good boy.
-妈妈这是威尔逊马鞍  -谢谢你
- Mama, here’s the Wilson saddle - Thank you.
别担心  我们一会就喂你吃东西
Don’t worry, we’ll get you food in a minute
妈妈  新家里有地方放小马吗
Mama, will we have space for our horses in our new home?
当然有  小宝贝  宫殿里有很多房间
Of course we will, darling, we'll have a palace of rooms.
屈膝礼
Curtsey.
陛下
Your Majesty.
登基怎么样
How was it?
我在努力熟悉公文
I'm trying to familiarise myself with what a state paper looks like.
鲍德温先生来的信件  我一个字都没看懂
A despatch from Mr Baldwin which I don't understand a word of.
大卫的财务状况
David's finances.
圣诞演说
The Christmas broadcast -
我觉得这是个错误
I think that might be a mistake.
别担心了
Don't worry about that.
还有加冕典礼计划
Plans for the Coronation -
这或许是个更大的错误
I think that's an even bigger mistake.
我不是国王
I'm not a King.
我只是个海军军官
I'm a naval officer.
我只知道怎么做海军军官
It's the only thing I know.
我不属于这里  我不是国王
I'm not here. I'm not a King.
对不起
I'm sorry.
别  别这样
Please...please.
亲爱的  亲爱的
Dear, dear man...
你知道吗  我两次拒绝你的求婚
You know... I refused your first two marriage proposals,
不是因为我不爱你
not because I didn't love you,
而是因为我不能忍受皇室的生活
but because I couldn't bear the idea royal life.
不能忍受四处出访和公共责任
Couldn't bear the idea of a life of tours and public duties,
生活不再属于我们自己
a life that no longer was really to be my own.
不过后来我想
But then I thought...
他是结巴太好了
he stammers so beautifully...
大家会放过我们
they'll leave us alone.
支持国王  上帝保佑他
等国王来道歉  那要等很久
Waiting for a king to apologize, one can wait rather a long wait.
恐怕我们迟到了一会
I'm afraid we're slightly late.
这就是我家  莫特尔去打桥牌了
This is home. Myrtle's at bridge.
我让孩子们都出去
I've made sure the boys are out.
太好了
It's lovely.
非常好
Absolutely lovely.
我能坐这吗
May I sit down?
当然可以
Yes, of course.
喝点茶吧  夫人
Would you like some tea, Ma'am?
好的  我自己来就行
Yes. I'll help myself.
你们聊吧
Off you go...
还是需要我强迫你们
Or must I knock your heads together?
这是我欠你的一先令
Here's your shilling,
我明白
I understand...
你之前的意思了  罗格
what you were trying to say, Logue.
我做错了
I went about it the wrong way.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
所以  我来了
Now here I am.
民众准备好
Is the nation ready for
听我的两分钟无声广播了吗
two minutes of radio silence?
所有结巴都害怕自己又回到原点
Every stammerer always fears they will fall back to square one.
我不会让这个情况发生的
I don't let that happen.
如果我做的不好
If I fail in my duty...
大卫就会回来
David could come back.
我看到那些布告了
I've seen the placards
天佑吾王
God save Our King!?
他们指的不是我
They don't mean me.
历史上每一位君主的继任
Every other monarch in history
都是在前任去世或者命不久矣的情况下
succeeded someone who was dead, or just about to be.
而我的前任不仅活着  还活得很好
My predecessor is not only alive, but very much so.
真是一团糟
What a bloody mess!
我甚至不能发表一次圣诞演说
I can't even give them a Christmas Speech.
像您父亲曾经那样
Like your Dad used to do?
没错
Precisely.
他已经不在了
He's not here anymore.
不  他还在  就在我给你的一先令上
Yes he is. He's on that shilling I gave you.
随便都能送人
Easy enough to give away.
您不用总带着他的影子
You don't have to carry him around in your pocket.
或者你哥哥的影子
Or your brother.
您无需害怕那些
You don't need to be afraid of
您五岁时候害怕的东西
the things as you were afraid of when you were five.
您已经独立自主  博迪
You're very much your own man, Bertie.
是吗
Am I?
你的脸会印在下一批硬币上  哥们
Your face is next, mate.
莱昂纳尔
Lionel?
莫特尔
Myrtle!
-没事吧  -没事
- Is it alright? - Yes.
博迪  过来
Bertie, come here.
-你还好吧  罗格  -还好
- Are you alright, Logue? - Yes.
-要出去吗  -相信我  这很重要
- Shall we go through? - Trust me. It's important.
怎么了
What is it?
-陛  陛  -第一次叫陛下就好
- Your... Your... - It's your Majesty? The first time.
之后可以叫夫人  别读错了
After that, it's Ma'am,As in Ham, not Malm as in Palm.
我没跟她讲过我们的事
I haven't told her about us.
先坐下  放松
Sit down, relax.
你丈夫叫我丈夫博迪
I'm told your husband calls my husband Bertie
而我丈夫叫你丈夫莱昂纳尔
and my husband calls your husband Lionel.
我想你应该不会叫我莉斯
I trust you won't call me Liz.
陛下  你可以叫我罗格夫人
Your Majesty, you may call me Mrs Logue, Ma'am.
见到你很高兴  罗格夫人
Very nice to meet you, Mrs Logue.
罗格  我们不能一直站这
Logue, we can't stand here all day.
我们可以的  我得等个合适的时候
Yes we can. Look, I need to wait for the right moment.
罗格你这样像胆小鬼
Logue, you're being a coward!
你说的没错
You're damn right.
出去吧  伙计
Get out there, man!
嗨  亲爱的莫特尔
Hello, Myrtle darling!
你回来早了  我相信你们已经见过面了
You're early. I believe you two have met!
但是  我想你应该还没见过
But I didn't think, you know...
国王乔治六世
King George the Sixth.
很高兴见到你
It's very nice to meet you.
陛下们要留下吃晚饭吗
Will their Majesties be staying to dinner?
我们也想留下来  谢谢你的好意
We would love to, such a treat, but alas...
但是有约在身  真遗憾
a previous engagement. What a pitty.
-主教大人  -欢迎您  陛下
- Archbishop. - Welcome, your Majesty.
多么壮观的改造  阁下
What a glorious tranformation, Sir.
请允许我们继续准备
I hope you'll forgive us if we continue our preparations.
现在请允许我为您介绍仪式的过程
And now you will allow me to guide you through the ceremony.
我们从西门进来  然后到中殿
We begin of course at the West door, then into the nave.
我听说您所有讲话
I see you all your
都会被广播  主教大人
pronouncements are to be broadcast, Archbishop.
是的  无线电就像潘多拉的盒子
Ah, yes, wireless is indeed a Pandora's Box.
我恐怕还得批准新闻摄影的拍摄
I'm afraid I also have to permit the newsreel cameras.
我会亲自监督剪辑的
The product of which I shall personally edit.
真是毫不犹豫
Without momentary hesitation.
这是哈里大街的罗格医生
This is Doctor Logue of Harley Street.
他是我的语言治疗师
He's my speech therapist.
-大人  -如果知道
- Your Grace. - Had I known
陛下您在寻医
that Your Majesty was seeking assistance
我一定会亲自给您推荐人选的
I should've made my own recommendation.
罗格医生
Dr. Logue...
会  会出席加冕礼
will be attending the Coronation.
我可以去跟教长说一下
Well of course I shall speak with the Dean,
但会很困难
but it was extremely difficult.
我想让他坐到国王的包厢里
I should like the Doctor to be seated in the King's Box.
但那是给您的家人准备的  阁下
But members of your Family will be seated there, Sir.
这正是为何坐那里合适
That is why it's suitable.
大人如果你不介意的话
And now, if you don't mind Your Grace,
我们需要场地准备
we need the premises.
老兄  这可是威斯敏斯特教堂
My dear fellow, this is Westminster Abbey!
教堂必须为陛下准备
The Church must prepare his Majesty.
我的准备也一样重要
My preparations are equalized in important
如果你不介意的话  最好清场
With complete privacy, if you don't mind.
我也希望这样  大人
Those are my wishes, Your Grace.
今晚教堂就交由陛下使用
I shall place the Abbey at Your majesty's disposal...
容我告退  陛下
this evening. Your Majesty.
看  他又来了
Look, he comes again.
我不敢相信我正走在
I can't believe I'm walking on
乔叟  韩德尔和狄更斯的墓上
tombs of Chaucer and Handel and Dickens.
准备好了吗  我们开始吧
Everything alright? Let's get cracking.
我不是来这彩排的  罗格医生
I'm not here to rehearse, Doctor Logue.
叫我莱昂纳尔
Call me Lionel.
是啊  你一直  都不管自己叫医生
True, you... never... called yourself "Doctor."
是我这么叫你
I did that... for you.
没有培训  没有文凭  没有资质
No training, no... diploma, no... qualifications.
只有一身的胆量
Just a... great deal of nerve.
这是秘密审问吗
The star chamber inquisition, is this?
你要求信任  和充分的平等
You asked trust and... total equality.
博迪  我听了你在温布利的演讲
Bertie, I heard you at Wembley.
我当时在场
I was there.
我的儿子劳里说  爸爸
My son Laurie said dad,
你能不能帮帮这个可怜人
do you think you could help that poor man??
怎么帮  就凭一个失败的演员
What, as a failed actor!?
这是事实  我不是一个医生
It's true, I'm not a doctor,
而且  我确实当过演员
and yes I acted a bit,
我在俱乐部朗诵  在学校教演讲
Well I recited in pubs and taught elocution in schools.
当大战来临
When the Great War came,
我们的士兵从前线回来
all our Soldiers were returning straight from the front,
很多人得了炮弹休克症
a lot of them shell-shocked,
无法开口说话
unable to speak
有人跟我说  莱昂纳尔  你这么会演讲
somebody said, Lionel, you're very good at all this speech stuff.
你能帮帮这些可怜的人吗
Do you think you can possibly help these poor buggers.?
我做了肌肉治疗练习放松
I did muscle therapy, exercise, relaxation,
但是我知道要治好还需要更多
but I knew I had to go deeper.
这些可怜的年轻人害怕的大叫
These poor young blokes had cried out in fear,
却没有人倾听
no-one was listening to them.
我的工作就是让他们相信自己的声音
My job was to give them faith in their own voice
让他们知道有个朋友在用心倾听
and let them know that a friend was listening.
博迪  这一定让你想到自己
That must ring a few bells with you, Bertie.
你说得自己真高尚
You give a very noble account of yourself.
你去打听  这都是事实
Make inquiries. It's all true.
我都打听过了
Inquiries have been made!
你不知道多少人在找我的麻烦
You have no idea who I have breathing down my neck?
我为你做担保
I vouched for you
可你却连文凭都没有
and you have no... credentials.
可我成功治好了很多人
But lots of success!
我拿不出证书给你看
I can't show you certificate -
那时没有什么培训机构
there was no training then.
我会的一切都来自于经验
Everything I know I know from experience,
是那场战争  给我的经验
and that war... was some experience.
我的牌子上写的是  L・ 罗格  治疗言语缺陷
My plaque says, "L. Logue, Speech Defects."
没有医生两个字
No Dr., there are no letters after my name.
把我关进监狱好了
Lock me in the Tower.
如果可以我早就关了
I would if I could!
-以什么罪名  -欺诈罪
- On what charge? - Fraud!
战争一触即发
With war looming,
你让一个不能说话的国王坐上王位
you've saddled this nation with a voiceless King.
你毁了我的家庭幸福
You destroyed the happiness of my family.
所有这一切都是为了欺骗
All for the sake of ensnaring a star...
一个你根本就无法救治的明星病人
patient you couldn't possibly hope to assist!
就像疯子国王乔治三世
It'll be like mad... King George the Third,
我就是口吃的疯子国王乔治
there'll be mad King George the stammerer,
在人民最需要的时候让他们失望
who let his people down so badly in their hour of need!
你这是干什么  起来  你不能坐在这儿  快起来
What're you doing? Get up! You can't sit there! Get up!
为什么不能  这就是把椅子
Why not? It's a chair.
不  那不只是一把椅子  那是  那是
No, that's not a chair, that is... that is...
那是圣爱德华的王座
That is Saint Edward's Chair!
有人随便在上面刻了自己的名字
People have carved their names on it.
这把椅子是让历任国王和女王
That chair is the seat on which every King and Queen---
下面还有块大石头
It's held in a place by a large rock!
那是来自斯昆的石头
That's the Stone of Scone yard,
-你亵渎一切  -你相信这套吗
- you are trivialising everything. - You believe such bollocks.
你亵渎一切
You're trivialising everything!
我可不在乎有多少...
I don't care how many royal...
-听我说  听我说  -...皇族蠢货坐在这椅子上
- Listen to me. Listen to me! - ...arse have sat in this chair.
-听我说  -听你说  凭什么
- Listen to me... ! - Listen to you?! By what right?
神授王权  我是你的国王
By the divine right, if you must! I'm your King!!!
不  你不是  你自己告诉过我
No you're not! You told me so yourself.
你说过你并不想做国王
You said you didn't want it.
那我为什么还要浪费时间听你说话
Why should I waste my time listening to you?
因为我有权被倾听
Because I have a right to be heard!
-听你说什么  -我有权说话
- Heard as what?! - I HAVE A VOICE!!!
没错
Yes you do.
你有毅力
You have such a perservance,
博迪  你是我见过的最勇敢的人
Bertie, you're the bravest man I know.
你会成为一个非常好的国王
And you'll make a bloody good king.
这到底是怎么了
What on earth's going on,
-陛下  -一切正常  主教大人
- Sir? - It's quite alright, Archbishop.
罗格先生  我要告诉你
Mr Logue, you must know
我已经找了一个非常有资质的
that I found a replacement English specialist
英国专家来替代你
with impeccable credentials.
你的工作即将结束
Hence, your services will no longer be required.
你说什么
I'm sorry?
陛下的工作是咨询并听取建议
Your Majesty's function is to consult and be advised.
而您没有咨询  但刚得到建议
And you didn't consult, but you've just been advised.
我来给你提个建议
Now I advise you:
在这  种私人问题上  我会自己做决定
In this personal matter I will make my own decision.
我是为加冕国王的安危着想
My concern is for the head upon which I must place the crown.
我很感激  主教大人  但这是我自己的事情
I appreciate that Archbshop, but it's my head!
恕我告退
Your humble servant.
谢谢  博迪
Thank you Bertie.
我们排练吧  坐在您的位子上
Shall we rehearse? Come on upon your purge.
当您和伊丽莎白从西门进来之后
Now when you and Elizabeth enter through the West door,
您将听到赞歌  "我很高兴他们对我说"
you'll be greeted by the hymn "I was glad when they said onto me"
其实您也没那么高兴
Actually you won't be that glad,
因为他们会在那里唱很久
because they sing it for a very long time.
然后  你的朋友
Then your friend
主教大人会面向你走上台阶
the Archbishop will ponce up the stairs toward you
说  "陛下  您愿意宣誓吗"
and say "Sir, is Your Majesty willing to take The oath"
-"我愿意"  -你当然愿意
- "I am willing" - Course you are!
我得去最后面的位子听下效果
I'm gonna see what it sounds like in the cheap seats
保证连您的老保姆也能听到
so even your old nanny can hear.
"您愿意根据当地习俗统治不列颠  爱尔兰
"Will you govern your peoples of Great Britain, Ireland, Canada,
加拿大  澳大利亚  以及新西兰的人民吗"
Australia and New Zealand according to their lands and customs"
"我在此庄严承诺"
"I solemnly promise so do so."
大点声  我在后面听不到
Louder! I can't hear you up the back.
"我在此庄严承诺"
"I solemnly promise so do so."
很好
Very good!
您愿意以仁爱之心用法律和公正的判断
"Will you to your power cause Law and Justice, in Mercy,
来行使您的权利吗
to be executed in all your judgements?"
"我愿意"  "我愿意"
"I will." "I WILL!"
之后会有很长一段是关于坚持信念的
Then there's a very long bit about upholding the faith,
继续的也是废话  废话  废话  直到你最后说
goes on, rubbish, rubbish, rubbish. To which you finally say...
"我在这里所承诺的事
"The things which I have...herebefore promised,
我会一如既往的履行"
I will perform and keep."
上帝保佑
So help me God
你要说的就是这些  只有四句
And that's all you'll say. Four short responses,
亲吻那本书  在誓约上签字  你就是国王了
kiss the book and sign the oath and you're King.
很简单
Easy.
您差点把王冠戴反了  主教大人
You nearly crowned him backwards Archbishop!
有人把标志王冠反面的线弄掉了  陛下
Someone had removed the thread marking the back of the Crown, Sir.
别把线弄掉  主教大人
Try not lose the thread, Archbishop.
主教先生  我们看不到爸爸了
Archbishop, we're missing Papa.
非常好  非常好  主教大人
Very good, very good. Archbishop.
我希望国王和王后陛下对结果满意
Well, I hope Your Majesties are thrilled with the result.
现在你可以把机器关掉了
You could switch that machine off now.
不要  等等  继续放
No, wait, keep going.
请坐下吧  主教大人
Do have a seat, Archbishop.
爸爸  爸爸  他在说什么
Papa? Papa, what's he saying?
不知道  但他似乎说的很好
I don't know, but he seems to be saying it rather well.
陛下  我今天来见您
Sir, I have asked to see you today
是为了向您辞去首相的职务
in order to tender my resignation as Prime Minister.
听你这么说我很难过  鲍德温先生
I am so sorry to hear that, Mr Baldwin.
内维尔・张伯伦会接替首相之职
Neville Chamberlain will take my place as Prime Minister.
我在一个重大问题上做了错误的决定
It's a matter of principal. I was mistaken.
很难想象  这个世界上
I have found it impossible to believe
竟然有像希特勒这样
that there is any man in the World
如此缺乏道德感
so lacking in moral feeling as Hitler,
而这个世界也很可能会
but the world may be hurled for
再次陷入战争灾难的深渊
a second time into the abyss of destructive War.
一直以来丘吉尔都是对的
Churchill was right all along.
这就是希特勒的野心
This was always Hitler's intention.
在这危急时刻离开您  我感到很抱歉
I am many very sorry to leave you in this great time of crisis.
国王陛下  我很担心
I am very much afraid Sir,
您将面临最大的考验
that your greatest test is yet to come.
我在唐宁街10号的内阁会议室发表广播(1939年9月3日)
I am speaking to you from the cabinet room at 10 Downing Street.
今天早晨  英国驻柏林大使
This morning the British Ambassador in Berlin
提交了一份德国政府的最后声明
handed the German Government a final note
如果我们在11点之前没有得到知会
stating that unless we heard from them by 11 oclock
既是表示德国已经做好准备
that they were prepared at once
立即从波兰撤军
to withdraw their troops from Poland,
德英两国随即进入战争状态
a state of war would exist between us.
我要告诉你们的是
I have to tell you now
我们并未收到任何知会
that no such undertaking has been received,
因此  德英两国已经进入战争状态
and that consequently this country is at war with Germany.
最后  陛下  这是您的演讲稿  6点开始直播
At last Sir, here is your speech. You are on air at six.
时间不超过9分钟
I've timed it at just under nine minutes.
措辞经过充分推敲
The wording is fully approved.
首相先生也将在广播中发表演说
The Prime Minister will be joining you for the broadcast
这次广播将在全国
which will go out live across the Nation,
整个帝国及军队播放
the Empire and to our Armed Forces.
马上把罗格叫过来
Get Logue here immediately.
-那是防空气球  -是呀
- There's the barrage balloons. - Yes.
他们动作倒是挺快
They got them up there quickly.
我们是不是停车找掩体躲避
Should we pull over and find shelter?
不  继续开  没事的
No, go straight on. We'll be alright
-您好  先生  -我是莱昂纳尔・罗格
- Yes. Sir? - Lionel Logue.
哈特利大人正在等我  这是我的儿子劳里
Major Hartley's expecting me. This is my son Laury.
-谢谢  劳里  -一切顺利  爸爸
- Thank you, Laurie. - Good luck, Dad.
-这是国王的演讲稿  -谢谢  先生
- The King's Speech. - Thank you, Sir.
现在离直播还有大约40分钟
We have about forty minutes until the broadcast.
非常感谢  谢谢
Thank you very much. Thank you.
"我们前方也许是黑暗"
"there may be dark days ahead, and..."
再来一次
Try again.
"我们前方也许是黑暗"
"there may be dark days ahead, and..."
在卡住的地方停顿
Turn the hesitations into pauses,
然后自言自语说  天佑吾王
and say to yourself, God save the King
这句话我经常说  可明显没人听
I say that continuously, but apparently no one's listening.
长的停顿很好  在重大场合更显庄重
Long pauses are good: they add solemnity to great occasions.
那我就是最为庄重的国王
Then I'm the solemnest king who ever lived.
莱昂纳尔  如果我是国王  权利何在
And Lionel, if I am to be King... where is my power?
我能  我能组织内阁吗
Can I... Can I form a Government?
我能  我能征税或宣战吗  不能
Can I... Can I levy a tax or declare a war? No!
而我是所有职权的代表  为什么
Yet I am the seat of all authority. Why?
因为民众认为我讲话是为了他们
Because the Nation believes that when I speak, I speak for them.
但我却不善于讲话
Yet I cannot speak!
我们从头再来一遍  "在这一庄严时刻"
Let's take it all again from the top. "In this grave hour"
"在这一庄严时刻"  日  日  日
"In this grave hour" fuck fuck fuck
也许是我们有史以来最生死攸关的时刻  混蛋  操  操
perhaps the most fateful in our history bugger shit shit
我要向所有家庭
I send to every household of my...
就算我唱着说  "人"也总是很难发音
You see "P" Is always difficult, even when I'm singing.
遇到"人"的时候用"一个人"代替
Bounce onto it "A-peoples", not "People".
"一个人"   "...大英人民...
"A-peoples" ...household of my
的所有家庭  无论是在国内还是海外"
peoples both at home and overseas..."
很好
Beaut.
"传达这一消息"
...this message, doo-dah,
"怀着同样的深刻情感"
"...spoken with the same depth of feeling," doo-dah-dey,
"对你们每个人说  就好像我在"  操  日  混蛋
"...for each one of you as if I were able to" shit fuck bugger
和你们面对面交流
cross your threshold and speak to you"
你要在脑子里想  我有权力要你们都听到
In your head, now: I have a right to be bloody well heard!?
都听到  都听到  都听到我说话
Bloody well heard, bloody well heard, bloody well heard myself!
来段华尔兹  动起来  动作流畅
Now Waltz. Move! Get continuous movement.
"对大多数人来说  在有生之年  我们第二次..."
"For the second time in the lives of most of us we are at..."
-"我们"要停顿一下  -莱昂纳尔  我做不来
- We are...?Take a pause. - Lionel, I can't do this.
博迪  你可以的
Bertie, you can do it.
-再看一下最后一段  -博迪  时间到了
- Have a look at the last paragraph. - Bertie, it's time.
-主教大人  -国王陛下
- Archbishop. - Your Majesty.
这是个伟大的时刻  陛下
A great moment, Sir.
-首相  -国王陛下
- Prime Minister. - Your Majesty.
我们又见面了  真快
Nice to see you again, so soon.
你能来很好  我相信你刚度过了繁忙的一天
Good of you to be here, I'm sure you've had rather a busy day.
希望我们不会再被那些
Let's hope we have no more
该死的警报声打断  阁下
interruptions from those damned sirens, Sir.
或者那些可怜的小狗们
Or the wretched dogs.
-恭喜你荣任海军大臣  -谢谢国王陛下
- Congratulations. First Lord of the Admiralty. - Your Majesty.
很长一段路
The long walk.
一切顺利  陛下
Good luck, Sir.
我也害怕这种仪器
I too dread this apparatus.
您知道吗  我也曾口吃
Had a speech impediment myself, you know.
-没听说过  -家族秘密  舌头打结
- I didn't. - Family secret. Tongue-tied.
手术风险很大
An operation was considered to be too dangerous.
最终我把它变成长处了
I eventually made an asset of it.
-谢谢  丘吉尔先生  -陛下请
- Thank you, Mr Churchill. - Sir.
亲爱的
Darling.
-还有多久  罗格  -不到3分钟  陛下
- How long, Logue? - Just under three minutes, Sir.
-伍德先生  -祝您好运  陛下
- Mr Wood. - Good luck, Your Majesty.
伍德先生
Mr Wood.
-你会被授予奖章  罗格  -拿来当杯垫
- You'll be decorated, Logue. - I made it cosy.
来点新鲜空气
Some fresh air.
来吧  亲爱的
There you are, Darling.
吃葡萄不吐葡萄皮
I'm thistle sifter, I've a sieve
of sifted thistles and a sieve on unsifted thistles.
吃葡萄不吐葡萄皮
I've a sieve of sifted thistles
and a sieve on unsifted thistles, because I'm...
博迪  亲爱的  别忘了开关
Bertie, darling, make sure it's not switched on!
记住红灯闪烁4次之后
Remember the red light will blink four times
我会叫他们关灯
and then I've asked them to turn it off,
因为不想
because we don't want that
让那只邪恶的眼睛一直盯着你
evil eye staring at you all the way through.
还有1分钟  陛下
One minute, sir.
我肯定你会做得很好
I am sure you will be splendid.
40秒  陛下
Fourty seconds, Sir.
罗格 不管结果如何
Logue, however this turns out,
我都不知道该如何感谢你
I don't know how to thank you for what you've done.
授爵行吗
Knighthood?
20秒
Twenty seconds.
抛开一切  只要对着我说话就好
Forget everything else and just say it to me.
对着我说  就像对朋友说
Say it to me, as a friend.
在这一庄严时刻
In this grave hour,
也许是我们有史以来生死攸关的时刻
perhaps the most fateful in our history,
我要向大英人民的每个家庭
I send to every household of my peoples,
无论是在国内
both at home
还是海外
and overseas
传达这一消息
this message
和你们一样
spoken with the same depth of feeling
怀着同样深刻的感受
for each one of you
就好像我在和你们
as if I were able to cross your threshold
面对面交谈
and speak to you myself.
对我们大多数人来说  有生之年
For the second time in the lives of most of us
我们再一次面临  面临战争
we are at... at war.
一次有一次
Over and over again
我们竭尽全力
we have tried to find
想为我们和那些如今成为敌人的人之间的差异
a peaceful way out of the differences between ourselves
找到和平的解决办法
and those who are now our enemies.
但终是突然
But it has been in vain.
我们被迫面临冲突
We have been forced into a conflict.
因为我们是被号召去挑战一种信条
For we are called, to meet the challenge of a principle
这种信条如果获胜
which, if it were to prevail,
将是对全世界文明秩序的
would be fatal to any civilized order
致命打击
in the world.
这种信条
Such a principle,
剥除所有伪装
stripped of all disguise,
无疑是一种简单的
is surely the mere
原始信条  那就是强权即真理
primitive doctrine that might is right.
为了我们所珍惜的一切
For the sake of all that we ourselves hold dear,
毫无疑问  我们不应拒绝迎接这种挑战
it is unthinkable that we should refuse to meet the challenge.
为了这个崇高的目标  在此
It is to this high purpose that I now call
我号召海内外所有的大英臣民
my people at home and my peoples across the seas,
将我们事业当作自己的事业
who will make our cause their own.
请你们保持镇静和坚定
I ask them to stand calm and firm,
在此危难之时团结一致
and united in this time of trial.
任务十分艰巨
The task will be hard.
我们前方也许是黑暗
There may be dark days ahead,
而战争也将不再局限于战场
and war can no longer be confined to the battlefield.
但我们只能做我们认为正确的事情
But we can only do the right as we see the right
并向上帝虔诚祈祷
and reverently commit our cause to God.
如果我们所有人都能坚定信念
If one and all we keep resolutely faithful to it,
那么  有上帝的庇佑
then, with God's help,
我们将取得胜利
we shall prevail.
非常好  博迪
Very good, Bertie.
你说"和"还是有点结巴
You still stammered on the "w"?
总得结巴几下  他们才知道是我
Had to throw in a few so they knew it was me.
恭喜您  国王陛下  一次真正的广播
Congratulations, your Majesty. A true broadcaster.
谢谢  伍德先生
Thank you, Mr Wood.
恭喜您  国王陛下
Congratulations, your Majesty.
-恭喜您  陛下  -谢谢
- Congratulations, your Majesty. - Thank you.
好了
Ready.
-行吗  -很好
- Good? - Perfect.
你的首次战争演讲  恭喜
Your first war time speech. Congratulations.
我还应做的更好
Expect I shall have to do a great deal more.
谢谢你  罗格
Thank you, Logue.
干得好  我的朋友
Well done, my friend.
谢谢您  国王陛下
Thank you, Your Majesty.
我知道你行的
I knew you'd be good.
谢谢你  莱昂纳尔
Thank you, Lionel.
继续吧
Onwards?
恭喜您  陛下
Congratulations, Sir.
您做得比我还好  陛下
Almost did it better than myself, Sir.
国王陛下  您让我难以言表
Your Majesty, I'm speechless.
恭喜您  陛下
Congratulations, Sir.
先生们
Gentlemen.
恭喜您  国王陛下
Congratulations, your Majesty.
你觉得爸爸怎么样  伊丽莎吧
So how was Papa, Elizabeth?
开始有些吞吐  但已经很好了  爸爸
Halting at first, but you got much better Papa.
亲一个
Bless you.
-你觉得呢  玛格丽特  -真是太精彩了  爸爸
- And how about you, Margaret? - You were just splendid, Papa.
那当然了
Of course I was.
都准备好了吗
We all ready?
来吧姑娘们
Come on girls.
1944年  乔治六世国王为莱昂纳尔・罗格授予了英国皇家维多利亚勋章
这是为感谢为君主个人服务而特别设立的唯一勋章
此后国王的每一次战争演讲都有莱昂纳尔陪同
通过广播  乔治六世国王成为国家抵抗的象征
莱昂纳尔和博迪在有生之年一直保持友谊